MSc Adv. Computer Science
University of Liverpool
Snr. IT Specialist & Software Developer
Cisco Network Professional

Emmanuel Jesse Ariko

Gender: Male

Email: eariko@outlook.com

Address: Daughters of Charity, Merseyside

Liverpool, United Kingdom.

PROFILE -

7+ years proven experience specializing in design, architecture, software and network engineering. Possess sound understanding of web development, Information Technology and ICT services including enterprise-level coding, network and internet support services.

Great expertise in Computer Science and Software development i.e. Web programmer, PHP developer, Systems specialist and Tester, Java developer, Linux specialist and C# developer. I am enthusiastic about learning new software, emerging technologies and being open minded with potential to grow self.

STRENGTH

- Communication
- Detail-oriented
- Critical thinking
- Leadership
- Strong Creativity
- Problem-solving
- Quick Leaner
- Positive Attitude

EDUCATION -

University of Liverpool

MSc Adv. Computer Science w Ind. (2018-2019)

University of Miami

CITI Human Research Certificate (2016 – 2016)

Kampala International University

BSc Computer Science (2010 – 2013)

SKILLS

Mobile: +447721084888

Web Technologies

HTML/CSS, AJAX, React, JavaScript, PHP

Programming Languages

C++, C#, Python, Java

Databases

MySQL, SQL Server, MS Access, Oracle

Development Methodologies

Agile, Waterfall, Test-Driven Development (TDD)

Technologies and Frameworks

Linux, IoT, Git, Windows Server & AD, Laravel

Software

JIRA, SharePoint, MS Teams, MS office, Cloud

Networking

LAN, WLAN, WAN, VSAT, Ubiquity, Cisco

Telecommunications

Microwave P2P Network, HF/VHF Equipment, Telephone

Security and Virtualization

Network Firewalls, PFSense, Gateways, VMWare

Others

Information Security (UNDSS), GCP Trained, DHIS2

Page | 1 of 6

Contact: +447721084888 e-mail: eariko@outlook.com

EXPERIENCE -

Software Developer

The Walton Centre NHS Foundation Trust (2019 - 2020)

- Developed and designed healthcare Software products - eP2. Pro-actively partook in software development process from initiation to finish.
- Delivered Information Management and Technology support services including Software design, application UI design, SQL Server Mgmt. and web development.
- Implemented Agile software methodology and completed software standardisation, testing and documentation.

Software Developer/ Researcher Aerodrums (2019)

- Implemented cross platform and multi modal IoT user interface design for the next generation Aerodrums air drumming instrument.
- Operated with Linux programming for Raspbian to develop applications that run on embedded systems using Raspberry Pi & NXP boards i.e. Microprogrammable chips.
- Coordinated with partner developers to design and select appropriate software tools for version control, embedding & testing Board Support packages (BSP).
- Effectively resolved software issues and bugs in time while dealing calmly and professionally with challenging circumstances/ research.

Student Support Researcher/ Worker University of Liverpool (2019)

- Researched on emerging technologies with focus on automation, embedded systems and sensor applications.
- Developed custom Linux distributions with Yocto-project for Raspberry Pi and NXP boards.
- Conducted research on headless units and computers for simultaneous AP / Client mode network connections.

Senior ICT Assistant

United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees - UNHCR (2018)

- Delivered enterprise-level IT and Telecoms support services. Installed, configured and maintained the LAN, WLAN and WAN networks.
- Oversaw and supported radio operators and ICT associates' duties. Conducted Windows Systems and Server Administration.
- Setup and operated VSAT satellite internet connectivity for field offices. Programmed HF and VHF radios for UNHCR.
- Delivered end-user and help-desk support services to staff at duty stations and at the field offices - Mbarara, Adjumani, Moyo.
- Implemented IT process improvement strategies, technical repairs, network installations and conducted inventory management. Networked designated refugee settlement sites to extend network services to on-site staff.

IT Systems Specialist

Mbale Clinical Research Institute (2017 – 2018)

- Developed open-source application for Clinical research and patient records administration - DHIS2. Built Institute website and internet resources for online presence.
- Instigated and maintained corporate network and enterprise systems.
 Performed hardware routine preventive maintenance, scheduled computer service requests resolution.
- Programmed Unifi Access Points (APs),
 Power Beams, Unifi Gateway and Unifi
 Controller. Installed new ICT devices
 and equipment including equipment
 replacement plus training medical staff.

ICT Specialist

Makerere University Walter Reed Project - MUWRP (2016 – 2017)

 Diagnosed and resolved ICT problems with network hardware and software systems. Supported Bio-medical and clinical research services.

Page | 2 of 6

- Upgraded network resources to improve overall performance of network services.
- Developed web apps and digitization software including implementation of MFiles documentation system, installed latest security systems / patches e.g.
 PFSense, and Enterprise resource planning systems – Ms Dynamics Nav.
- Provided end-user support, technical advice and resolutions via e-mail, phone and through collaborative software.
 Implemented server upgrades, Backups

IT Manager

Kampala Independent Hospital (2013 – 2015)

- Setup and maintained a systematic hospital information management system - Clinic Master. Developed inhouse health web-based applications.
- Implemented a secure hospital ICT infrastructure through both the LAN, WLAN and WAN. Improved integration of health services within the hospital systems merging all services in clinics, labs and theatres.
- Supervised ICT Service delivery, setup data management policies and ICT guidelines to support utilized computerbased medical equipment and resource.
- Designed and developed systems server and Client Environment which includes Windows Server, SQL Server, Windows OS, Linux, network Firewall, etc.

Software Developer

OGAS Solutions International (2014)

- Developed Google API applications for resource mapping and location-based services. Maintained, serviced and upgraded software and hardware in line with company development projects.
- Project management of software developed, scheduling tasks, code reviews, bug tracking, and execution of Google API apps. Provided Project documentation of existing and on-going applications created.
- Assessed the system requirements for

new projects. Designed UI layouts and applications to meet the business needs of OGAS Solutions. Evaluated existing projects and business needs to match the company Vision.

Web Developer & Instructor

Komasoft ICT Solutions (2011 - 2013)

- Programmed and designed responsive Web applications with advanced web technologies, media-queries/ PhoneGap technologies. Built and wrote code for Multimedia and database driven web applications with automation, created animations.
- Successfully conducted R&D programs in which trending technologies were being tested to improve exciting projects using new technologies of HTML5, CSS3 and WebGL at the time.
- Designed and hosted web applications for massive companies and start-ups in East-Africa such as Landy Industries, Okello Oryem & Advocates, Redeemed Church of Rwanda, MCRI, etc.
- Coached 12 students in Website designing, UI design and essentials of software development. Continued to nurture and guide new team members on web design, software testing and Graphics Design.

IT Supervisor & Observer

Democracy Monitoring Group - DEMGroup International (2011)

- Monitored and observed the daily election process for 2011 Uganda elections as an election observer.
 Provided instant SMS reports on any changes in the routine election process at my duty station.
- Operated and established Data compilation app to support Google PDA services. Partook in project planning and safeguarding all the Smart device security software and applications for information sharing.

Page | 3 of 6

ICT Specialist

Research International Uganda (2010 - 2011)

- Supported overall ICT end user support and operated as research data entry assistant. Implemented computer systems to support research, data collection and analysis.
- Managed company web hosting services, installation and enhancement of IT systems. Provided proposals for improvements of the smart-phone data entry apps and develop advanced web and mobile applications.
- Partook in hardware and software installations during system upgrades and maintenance of existing software applications. Assessed potential system risks and technical challenges.
- Conducted IT related trainings for new hires, users and technical teams as needed. Prepared suitable mitigation plans to risk and challenges faced.

Associate Network & System Administrator

Quality Supplies Computer World (2008 - 2010)

- Developed substantial operations and routines for systems Administration.
 Performed network and systems monitoring, troubleshooting and repairs of Local Area network (LAN), and WAN.
- Optimised network performance and boosted system services by applying innovative computer applications such as Cisco Network Magic Pro, Chrystalid Client, Print Manager, etc.
- Implemented Active Directory, network architecture, Windows Server-Client/ Workstation Administration, Research and identify solutions to software and hardware issues.
- Provided IT and Telecoms services to staff and Election Observers as well as maintaining and services mobile devices and Personal computers.

ICT Officer

TASO Mbale (2006 – 2007)

- Properly managed IT Infrastructure including computer networks, system administration & hardware installation. Identified, understood and gave priority to urgent issues and concerns to improve issue resolution time.
- Performed software upgrades, new installations and carried out routine procedures such as Preventive Maintenance for both hardware and software application systems. Helpdesk and Software Configuration Support.
- Server Administration for medium-level data resources - Epidata and Epi-Info, IT project Management and System Development, System Backup and disaster recovery implementations. in preparation for any data loss or system failure,

Languages

- English Fluent with excellent listening, speaking, and writing skills.
- French Elementary
- Swahili Basic
- Ateso Native

Awards

- Recognition Award for Highest Academic honours (2013) - BSc Computer Science
- Innovation Award winner (2015)
- Windle Trust Award (2018)
- Commonwealth Student Award (2018)
- Employee of the month Oct. & Nov. (2015)

Page | 4 of 6

Contact: +447721084888 e-mail: eariko@outlook.com